<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Sidney Redivivus, or, The opinion of the late Honourable Collonel Sidney as to civil government wherin is asserted and clearly proved, that the power of kings is founded in the consent of the people, who have a right to call them to an account for male-administration and to restore themselves to their native liberty : by which the late proceedings of the nation against James the II are justified : together with some reflections on what is said by ill men against the present government, by another hand.</title>
            <author>Sidney, Algernon, 1622-1683.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1689</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 34 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 11 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2012-10">2012-10 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A60215</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing S3764</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R10306</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">13779903</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 13779903</idno>
            <idno type="VID">101772</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A60215)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 101772)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 850:12)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Sidney Redivivus, or, The opinion of the late Honourable Collonel Sidney as to civil government wherin is asserted and clearly proved, that the power of kings is founded in the consent of the people, who have a right to call them to an account for male-administration and to restore themselves to their native liberty : by which the late proceedings of the nation against James the II are justified : together with some reflections on what is said by ill men against the present government, by another hand.</title>
                  <author>Sidney, Algernon, 1622-1683.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[4], 15, [1] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed for H. Smith and sold by most book-sellers,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1689.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in Huntington Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Political science --  England --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Political science --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-07</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-08</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-08</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-05</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="publisher_to_the_reader">
            <pb facs="tcp:101772:1"/>
            <head>THE PUBLISHER TO THE READER.</head>
            <opener>
               <salute>Courteous Reader,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>IF thou art a True <hi>Engliſh</hi>-Man, or Cordial <hi>Prote<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtant,</hi> I do not queſtion but the very Name of Collonel <hi>Sidney,</hi> will be ſufficient to Recommend what follows to thy Peruſal; ſeeing thou mayeſt juſtly expect ſomething con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiderable in the Writings of Him, who was ſo Conſiderable in Himſelf, that to accompliſh his Ruine, the late Court thought it worth their while to break through all the Methods of Law and Juſtice.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:101772:1"/>
            <p>
               <hi>Sidney Redivivus:</hi> OR THE OPINION Of the Late Honourable Collonel Sidney, As to Civil Government.</p>
            <p>WHEREIN Is Aſſerted and Clearly Proved, That the Power of Kings is Founded in the Conſent of the People; who have a Right to call them to an Account for Male-Adminiſtration, and to Reſtore themſelves to their Native Liberty.</p>
            <p>By which the late Proceedings of the Nation againſt <hi>James</hi> the II. are Juſtified.</p>
            <p>TOGETHER, With ſome Reflections on what is ſaid by ill Men againſt the Preſent Government, by another Hand.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed for <hi>H. Smith;</hi> And Sold by moſt Book-ſellers. MDCLXXXIX.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="half_title">
            <pb facs="tcp:101772:2"/>
            <p>Sidney Redivivus.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:101772:3"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <pb facs="tcp:101772:3"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb facs="tcp:101772:4"/>
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:101772:4"/>
            <head>
               <hi>Sidney Redivivus,</hi> OR THE Opinion of the Late Honourable Collonel <hi>SIDNEY,</hi> as to Civil Government, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>IT cannot be denyed, that we live in an Age wherein there have been univerſal endeavours to enſlave the Bodies and Souls of Men; nor is it leſs evident, that in theſe Nations the ſame Deſigns have been Proſecuted with very much Violence: And what party in the ſame, have been moſt ſubſervi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent to ſuch Intreagues, is ſo obvious, that they need not be named.</p>
            <p>The Writings and Sermons of particular, but Eminent Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vines; the Canons of a certain National Church: the Determi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nations of Judges, who valued themſelves as being of her Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munion, and the repeated into Nations of a great number of her Clergy, for the Chimera of Paſſive Obedience, gave occaſion to a frequent Raillery, as if the Doctrin of that Church were <hi>Cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vins,</hi> her Ceremonies the Popes, and that ſhe had nothing of her own but the Doctrin of Non-reſiſtance; ſo that like the Bird in the Fable, who would needs appear Fine in borrowed Feathers, being ſtript of what was not her property, ſhe became Naked and Ridiculous to all.</p>
            <p>No wonder then, that a certain ſort of Men pretending to her Communion, have incurred this fate, whoſe <hi>Shibboleth</hi> and Cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>racteriſtick ſome Years ago being Non-reſiſtance and Paſſive O<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bedience, have now betaken themſelves to contrary Practices, when they found the ſmart of Oppreſſion.</p>
            <pb n="2" facs="tcp:101772:5"/>
            <p> Whatever may be ſaid to the Honour, or excuſe of thoſe who have acted thus upon Change of Principle, or to their diſgrace who can pretend no ſuch Reaſon, my Opinion of it is, that Truth hath overcome, and that we may juſtly ſay, <hi>Tandem bona cauſa Triumphat.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>No leſs than that Omnipotence which made the Devils own Chriſt to be the Son of God (tho' they knew that he was come into the World to deſtroy their Works) hath forced a Teſtimo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny to the Native Rights of Mankind, from the very Mouths of thoſe Tyranogogues, who after an Elevation and Adoration of Abſolute Power; and Unaccountableneſs of Kings to any other than the Almighty, for above Twenty Years paſt, have by a Stupendious Providence of that God (whoſe Steps are in the Deep Waters, and his ways paſt finding out) been brought in open Courts of Juſtice by Arguments, and in the Field by Arms, to Impugne their own Idol of Non-reſiſtance; like ſome of the Arch-Flamens of old when Converted to Chriſtianity, who Arm<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed themſelves Cap-apee to overthrow thoſe Block Deities, which had ſometimes been the Objects of their Worſhip.</p>
            <p>Nor hath Providence only herein extorted from ſuch, a re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>markable Teſtimony to the Truth, but alſo an Ample Vindica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of thoſe who ſuffered for the ſame, under the Notion of Traytors, by <hi>perverting Law;</hi> and bad Chriſtians, by <hi>wreſted Divinity;</hi> but more eſpecially of that Honourable Patriot, whoſe Opinion as to Government we have now under conſidera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, by which being Dead he yet ſpeaketh, and Patroniz<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth the <hi>Good Old Cauſe;</hi> for which he Profeſſedly Died a Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tyr.</p>
            <p>His Opinion follows in his own Words, as Cited in the <hi>23d</hi> Page of his Tryal.</p>
            <p>That People muſt needs be the Judge of things happening be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tween them and <hi>him (meaning the King)</hi> whom they did not Conſtitute, that he might be Great, Glorious and Rich, but that he ſhould Judge them and Fight their Battles, or other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe do good unto them as they ſhould direct. In this Sence he is <hi>Singulis Major,</hi> and ought to be obliged by every Man
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:101772:5"/>in his Juſt and Lawful Commands tending to the Pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lick Good, and muſt be ſuffered to do nothing againſt it, nor in any reſpect more than the Law doth al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low.</p>
            <p>For this Reaſon <hi>Bracton</hi> ſaith, <q>That the King hath Three Superiours, <hi>Deum, Legem &amp; Parliamentum,</hi> that is, the Power Originally in the People of <hi>England,</hi> is Delegated to the Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liament; He is ſubject unto the Law of God as he is a Man; To the People, that make him a King, in as much as he is a King: The Law ſets a Meaſure unto that Subjection, and the Parliament Judges of the particular Caſes thereupon a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſing; he muſt be content to ſubmit his Intereſt unto theirs, ſince he is no more than any one of them in any other reſpect, than that he is by the Conſent of all raiſed above any o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther.</q>
            </p>
            <p>
               <q>If he doth not like this Condition, he may Renounce the Crown, but if he Receive it upon that Condition (as all Magi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrates do the Power they Receive) and Swear to perform it, he muſt expect, that the Performance will be Exacted, or Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venge taken by thoſe that he hath Betray'd.</q>
            </p>
            <p>If this be not ſo, I deſire to know of our Author, <hi>(meaning Sir</hi> Robert Filmer, <hi>againſt whoſe Opinion he Writes)</hi> how one or more Men came to be Guilty of Treaſon againſt the King, as <hi>Lex facit ut ſit reus:</hi> No Man can owe more unto him than unto any other, or he unto every other Man, by any Rule but the Law, and if he muſt not be Judge in his own Caſe, neither he nor any other by Power receiv'd from him would ever. Try any Man for an Offence againſt him, or the Law.</p>
            <p>If the King, or ſuch as he appoints, cannot Judge him, he can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not be Judged by the ways ordinarily known amongſt us; if he or others by Authority from him may Judge, he is Judge in his own Caſe, and we fall under that which he accounts the ut<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moſt of all abſurdites; if a remedy be found for this, he muſt ſay, that the King in his own Caſe may Judge the People, but the People muſt not Judge the King; becauſe it is theirs: that is to ſay, The Servants Entertained by the Maſter may Judge him, but the Maſter muſt not Judge the Servant whom he took
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:101772:6"/>only for his own uſe: The Magiſtrate is bound by no Oath or Contract to the People that Created him, but the People is bound to its own Creature the Magiſtrate.</p>
            <p>This ſeems to be the ground of all our Authors Follies; he cannot comprehend that Magiſtrates are for, or by the People, but makes this Concluſion, as if Nations were Created by, or for the Glory or Pleaſure of Magiſtrates, and affects ſuch a piece of Nonſenſe; it ought not to be thought ſtrange, if he repreſent as an Abſur'd thing, that the headleſs Multitude may ſhake off the Yoke when they pleaſe. But I would know how the Multi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tude comes under the Yoke, it is a badge of Slavery. He ſays, That the Power of the King is for the Preſervation of Liberty and Property. We may therefore change or take away Kings without breaking any Yoke, or that made a Yoke, which ought not to be one; the Injury therefore is in making or impoſing, and there can be none in breaking it. I know not why the Multitude ſhould be concluded to be headleſs, it is not always ſo. The <hi>Scots,</hi> when they ſlew <hi>James</hi> the III, had his Son to be their Head; and when they Depoſed and Impriſoned Queen <hi>Mary,</hi> the Earl of <hi>Murray</hi> and others, ſupplyed the want of Age that was in her Son; and in all the Revolutions we have had in <hi>England,</hi> the people have been headed by the Parliament, or the Nobility and Gentry that compoſed it; and when Kings failed of their Duties, by their own Autho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity called it. The Multitude therefore is not ever headleſs, but doth either find or create heads unto it ſelf, as occaſion doth require; and whether it be one man, or a few, or more, for a ſhort or a longer time, we ſee nothing more regular then its Motions. But they may, ſaith our Author, ſhake off the Yoke; and why may they not, if it prove uneaſie or hurtful unto them? Why ſhould not the <hi>Iſraelites</hi> ſhake off the Yoke of <hi>Pharoah, Jabin, Siſera,</hi> and others, that oppreſſed them?</p>
            <p>When <hi>Pride</hi> had changed <hi>Nebuchadnezzar</hi> into a Beaſt, what ſhould perſwade the <hi>Aſſyrians</hi> not to drive him out amongſt Beaſts, until God had reſtored unto him the Heart of a Man? When <hi>Tarquin</hi> had turned the Legal Monarchy of <hi>Rome</hi> into a moſt Abominable Tyranny, why ſhould not they Aboliſh it?
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:101772:6"/>And when the Proteſtants of the Low Countries were ſo grie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vouſly Oppreſſed under the Power of <hi>Spain,</hi> by the proud, Cruel and Savage Conduct of the Duke of <hi>Alva,</hi> why ſhould not they make uſe of all the means that God had put into their Hands, for their Deliverance? Let any Man, who ſees the preſent State of the Provinces, that then United themſelves, judge whether it is better for them to be as they are, or in the Condition unto which his Fury would have Reduced them, unleſs they had, to pleaſe him, Renounced God and their Religion: Our Author may ſay, <hi>They ought to have ſuffered.</hi> The King of <hi>Spain,</hi> by their Reſiſtance, loſt thoſe Countries; and that they ought not to have been Judges in their own caſe. For which I An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwer, That by Reſiſting, they laid the Foundation of many Churches, that have produced multitudes of Men, Eminent in Gifts and Graces, Eſtabliſhed a moſt Glorious and Happy Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon-Wealth, that hath been ſince its firſt beginning, the ſtrong<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt Pillar of the Proteſtant Cauſe, now in the World, and a place of Refuge unto thoſe, who in all places of <hi>Europe</hi> have been Oppreſſed for the Name of Chriſt; whereas had they Slaviſhly, and I think I may ſay Wickedly as well as Fooliſhly, ſuffered themſelves to be Butchered, if they had left thoſe empty Provin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces under the Power of Anti-Chriſt, where the Name of God is no otherwiſe known, then to be Blaſphemed.</p>
            <p>If the King of <hi>Spain</hi> deſired to keep his Subjects, he ſhould have Governed them with more Juſtice and Mercy, when contrary unto all Laws, both Humane and Divine, he ſeeks to deſtroy thoſe he ought to have preſerved; he can blame none but himſelf, if they deliver themſelves from his Tyranny; and when the mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter is brought to that, that he muſt not Reign, or they over whom he would Reign muſt periſh, the matter is eaſily decided, as if the Queſtion had been asked in the time of <hi>Nero</hi> or <hi>Domi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tian,</hi> whether they ſhould be left at liberty to deſtroy the beſt part of the World, as they endeavoured to do, or it ſhould be Reſcued from their deſtruction; and as for the Peoples being Judges in their own caſe, it is plain, they ought to be the only Judges, becauſe it is their own, and only concerns them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves.</p>
            <pb n="6" facs="tcp:101772:7"/>
            <p> So much for his Opinion of <hi>Civil Government</hi> as extracted from that part of the Book for which he was Condemned; and after ſerious Peruſal of which, I doubt not but the Candid Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der will be convinced, that ſuch a Fragment deſerves taking up, and is worthy of being revived, to let the Nation ſee the loſs they have in being Robb'd of the whole, but much more of ſo Noble a Patriot, as was the Author of it, Collonel <hi>Sidney.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>In the next place I ſhall add what he delivered upon the ſame Subject, in his Paper to the Sheriffs on the Scaffold, at his Execution, <hi>December</hi> 7th, 1683.</p>
            <p>If he (meaning Sir <hi>Robert Filmer</hi>) might publiſh unto the World his Opinion, That all men are Born under a neceſſity derived from the Laws of God and Nature, to ſubmit unto an Abſolute Kingly Government, which could be reſtrained by no Law, or Oath; and that he that hath the Power, whether he came unto it by Creation, Election, Inheritance, Uſurpation, or any other way, had the right; and none muſt oppoſe his Will, but the Perſons and Eſtates of his Subjects muſt be in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diſpenſably ſubject unto it. I know not why I might not have publiſhed my Opinion to the contrary, without the Breach of any Law I have yet known.</p>
            <p>I might as freely as he, publickly have declared my Thoughts, and the Reaſons upon which they were grounded; and I per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwaded to believe, That God had left Nations unto the li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berty of ſetting up ſuch Governments as beſt pleaſed them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves. That Magiſtrates were ſet up for the good of Nati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, not Nations for the Honour or Glory of Magiſtrates.</p>
            <p>That the Right and Power of Magiſtrates in every Country, was that which the Laws of the Country made it to be.</p>
            <p>That thoſe Laws were to be obſerved; and the Oaths taken by them, having the force of a Contract between Magiſtrate and People, could not be violated without danger of Diſſolving the whole Fabrick.</p>
            <p>That Uſurpation could give no Right; and the moſt dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gerous of all Enemies unto Kings, were they, who raiſing their Power to an Exorbitant height, allowed unto Uſurpers all the Rights belonging unto it:</p>
            <pb n="7" facs="tcp:101772:7"/>
            <p> That ſuch Uſurpation being ſeldome compaſſed without the Slaughter of the Reigning Perſon or Family, the worſt of all Villanies was thereby rewarded with the moſt Glorious Priviledges.</p>
            <p>That if ſuch Doctrines were received, they would ſtir up Men to the Deſtruction of Princes, with more Violence than all the Paſſions that have hitherto raged in the Hearts of the moſt unruely.</p>
            <p>That none could be ſafe, if ſuch a reward were propoſed unto any that could deſtroy them.</p>
            <p>That few would be ſo gentle as to ſpare even the beſt, if by their Deſtruction a Wild Uſurper could become Gods Anoint<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, and by the moſt Execrable Wickedneſs Inveſt himſelf with that Divine Character.</p>
            <p>This is the Scope of the whole Treatiſe, the Writer gives ſuch Reaſons as at preſent did occur unto him to prove it. This ſeems to agree with the Doctrines of the moſt Reverenced Authors of all Times, Nations and Religions. The beſt and wiſeſt Kings have ever acknowledged it. The preſent King of <hi>France</hi> hath declared, that Kings have that happy want of Power, that they can do nothing contrary to the Laws of their Country, and grounds his Quarrel with the King of <hi>Spain, Anno</hi> 1667, upon that Principle — King <hi>James</hi> in his Speech to the Parliament <hi>Anno</hi> 1603. doth in the high<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt degree Aſſert it, the Scriptures ſeem to declare it.</p>
            <p>If the Expulſion of <hi>Tarquin,</hi> the Inſurrection againſt <hi>Nero,</hi> the Slaughter of <hi>Caligula</hi> or <hi>Domitian,</hi> the Tranſlation of the Crown of <hi>France</hi> from <hi>Merovius</hi> his Race unto <hi>Pepin,</hi> and from his Deſcendants unto <hi>Hugh Capet</hi> be not good Acts of State, there is not a King in the World has any Title to the Crown he bears, nor can have any, unleſs he could deduce his Pedigree from the Eldeſt Son of <hi>Noah,</hi> and ſhow, that the Succeſſion had ſtill continued in the Eldeſt of the Eldeſt Line, and ſo Deduced to him.</p>
            <p>Every one may ſee what advantage this would be to all the Kings of the World, and whether that failing, it were not better for them to acknowledge their Crowns by the Conſent of Willing Nations, or to have no better Title unto them than
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:101772:8"/>Uſurpation and Violence, which by the ſame ways may be taken from them.</p>
            <p>So much as to this Subject in his laſt Speech, by which you may ſee, that as he lived in this Opinion, he was not afraid to Die in it, as being fully perſwaded of its agreeableneſs to Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vine Truth, at whoſe Bar he was in a few Minutes to receive a juſter Sentence than that by which he ſuffered. And the worſt that I ſhall wiſh that Inſtrument of Cruelty who was his Judge, is, That ſeeing he is far from being ſo ſit to Live in this World, he may be as fit to go into another, as that Worthy Gentleman was; but this I am confident of, he will never be able to reflect upon his own Tyranny, and the Abetting of it in others, with that Serenity of Mind, and Tranquility of Soul, as this Noble Patriot did, upon his Oppoſition to it, when according to the good Laws of the Kingdom, and the Righteous Judgment of God, Inquiſition ſhall be made for Blood; of which a great deal is to be found in his Skirts that threatens him with Divine Vengeance, according to the Prayer of this Worthy Gentle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man, <hi>That if Inquiſition was to be made after Blood, it might fall upon thoſe who Perſecuted him for Righteouſneſs ſake.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>It hath been an old and true Obſervation, that the Blood of the Saints is the Seed of the Church; and I do not know, but it may be alſo ſaid, that the Blood of Patriots is the Seed of Aſſerters of the Peoples Liberty; for ſince the Effuſion of this Gentlemans Blood, and that of others, we have had a plentiful Harveſt of ſuch as have Aſſerted the Civil and Religious Rights of the Nations; and that nothing might be wanting to Crown our Mercy, we are Bleſſed with a Magnanimous and Religious King, who as he ventured all for their Redemption, will do the ſame for their preſervation.</p>
            <p>But notwithſtanding of what is here ſaid by this Worthy Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thor, and may others upon this Subject; there is a Party in the Nation, who are ſo much under the Conduct of their own Luſts, that to have a full Liberty of Wallowing in them; they ſurceaſed no endeavours to bring others and themſelves too, under the Tyranny and Luſts of the two Late Kings, and
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:101772:8"/>are now enraged to ſee the People Delivered, tho' not many Months ago they were loudeſt in their Clamours againſt the Male Adminiſtration of the Late <hi>James</hi> the II. when they found themſelves in hazard of Smarting by the Rod they had prepared for others. Whereupon break<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing through all the pretended tyes of Allegiance, which they had ſo often Ratified with Dam 'em, and Sink 'em, and Swallowing down of brim-full Bumpers, they were very active in over-turning his Government, either by de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerting or appearing againſt him.</p>
            <p>Amongſt this kind of Men, who deſpiſe Dominion and ſpeak evil of Dignities, are theſe Murmurs and Diſcontents, which do occaſion ſuch a ferment at this time in the Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion. It is not unworth the while to obſerve the differ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence betwixt the Diſcontented now, and ſuch as were ſo in the two laſt Reigns, the latter being generally all who had any Sobriety in their Practice, or Zeal for the true Religion and Laws of the Kingdom, whether Church-men or Diſſenters; the former being not one in a Hundred other than the Ignorant and Profane, who are a Scandal to all Humane Society, and particularly to the Church of <hi>England</hi> under whoſe Name (as Vermine under a Roof) they Shelter themſelves; and indeed there is no other way left for that Society to rid themſelves of the Infamy which is likely to fall upon the whole becauſe of them, but by ſome publick Teſtimony to declare their Abhorrence of ſuch; deny them their Communion, and Preach up Obedience now, as much as in the two Late Reigns, there being infinitely more Reaſon to do ſo at this time, than there was at that: His Preſent Majeſty (whom God long Preſerve) having by the Miraculous Hand of the Omnipotent, been made our Redeemer, by the Conſent of the People, an undoubted Title to the So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veraignty, and by his Prudent and Legal Adminiſtration, not only acquir'd a Right to an Obedience from Fear, but Love, the moſt Sacred and Inviolable Foundation of Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minion.</p>
            <pb n="10" facs="tcp:101772:9"/>
            <p> Theſe Inſtruments of wickedneſs, that they may paſs their Black Deſigns of re-enſlaving the Nations, have recourſe to their old Exploded Arguments, that the King is accountable to none but God, That they have an Here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ditary Right of Succeſſion; and that the Accuſations as to the Earl of <hi>Eſſex's</hi> Murther; the Impoſing of a Prince of <hi>Wales, &amp;c.</hi> have never been proved againſt the Late King, and that therefore he has been unjuſtly dealt with.</p>
            <p>Theſe and others of the ſame ſort, are as conſidently talked of amongſt ſuch Men, as if they had never been concerned in contrary Practices, either by Acting, Deſert<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, or Silence; in all which as they were Influenced by a corrupt Principle of miſtaken Self Intereſt then, they are by the ſame engaged in oppoſite Practices now. I ſhall touch a little upon thoſe Arguments, and Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clude.</p>
            <p>That the King as King [that is, Governing according to Law] is accountable to any but God, few will deny; becauſe therein he Acts according to his Commiſſion from the body of the People, who it is to be ſuppoſed are con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tent to ſee the ſame put in Execution; and there being no Power Superiour to theirs but Gods, there can be no other to call him to an Account in that Caſe.</p>
            <p>But the Queſtion is, Whether the Perſon Cloathed with the Kingly Authority, and Acting beyond, or contrary to his Commiſſion, be for ſuch Acts accountable to them from whom he Receiv'd his Commiſſion? I ſuppoſe it will readily be granted he is. But here ſome Object, That the King has his Commiſſion only from God, and conſequent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly accountable to no other.</p>
            <p>I Anſwer, God never Inſtituted any ſuch Kings as had their Commiſſion only from him; for even thoſe very Kings which he himſelf Named, as <hi>Saul, &amp;c.</hi> were made Kings, and ſet up by the People upon certain conditions, as is
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:101772:9"/>evident from <hi>Deut.</hi> 17.14. <hi>When thou art come into the Land which the Lord thy God giveth thee — and ſhalt ſay,</hi> (note) <hi>I will ſet a King over me. V.</hi> 15. <hi>Thou ſhalt in any wiſe ſet him King over thee — One from among thy Brethren ſhalt thou ſet King over thee; Thou mayſt not ſet a Stranger over thee</hi> — Then follows the Limits — <hi>He ſhall not Multiply Horſes. V.</hi> 16. <hi>Neither Multiply Wives.</hi> (Much leſs Whores, as our Late King did, and yet the Church not ſo honeſt as to deny him their Communion; nor reprove him as Old <hi>Cranmer</hi> did <hi>Henry</hi> the Eighth, whom he Preſented with a Bible, having on the Out ſide of it in Capitals, <hi>Whore-mongers and Adulterers God will puniſh.</hi>) V. 18. <hi>He ſhall Write him a Copy of their Laws.</hi> V. 19. <hi>And it ſhall be with him, that he may Read therein all the Days of his Life.</hi> V. 20. <hi>That his Heart be not lifted up above his Brethren, and that he turn not aſide from the Commandment to the Right Hand, or to the Left,</hi> &amp;c. From which Texts I think it is ſufficiently evident, that the Power of making the King was in the People, at whoſe de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſire that Change of Government was made, and that he was to be Limited, and the Conditions preſcribed, from which he was to turn aſide to neither Hand; ſo that ſome Hundreds of Years before they ſet up a King over them, they had Statutes fixed to regulate him in his Office, that his Heart ſhould not be lifted up above his Brethren.</p>
            <p>It is yet clearer, that the People Created <hi>Saul</hi> King, from 1 <hi>Sam.</hi> 11.15. <hi>And all the People went to</hi> Gilgal, <hi>and there they made</hi> Saul <hi>King before the Lord in</hi> Gilgal.</p>
            <p>We find alſo, that <hi>Samuel,</hi> tho' he had been their Chief Magiſtrate, yet he reckoned himſelf accountable to the People, and therefore deſires them to Witneſs againſt him if he had been Guilty of Fraud, Oppreſſion, or Bribery, whereof they Solemnly acquitted him, 1 <hi>Sam.</hi> 12.</p>
            <p>Nor do we find, that they thought their new Soveraign Abſolute or uncontroulable, for they would not ſuffer him to Execute his own Son <hi>Jonathan,</hi> becauſe he acted unknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ingly, contrary to his Fathers Raſh Oath, 1 <hi>Sam.</hi> 14. and
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:101772:10"/>afterwards we find <hi>David</hi> put himſelf in a poſture of De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fence againſt him when he Acted Tyrannically.</p>
            <p>So when <hi>David</hi> Succeeded, we Read of a Stipulation be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tween him and the People who made him King, 2 <hi>Sam.</hi> 5.3. and the ſame Method was obſerved throughout, as none who have Read and obſerved the Book of the Kings and Chro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nicles can be ignorant of.</p>
            <p>And that the People thought their Kings accountable to them, and anſwerable for their Actions, appears from the oppoſition, made to the Kings General and his Army by the City of <hi>Abel,</hi> and the Wiſe Womans Queſtions, <hi>Why he would Swallow up the Inheritance of the Lord?</hi> To which <hi>Joab,</hi> tho' a Stern and Valiant Captain, return'd a very modeſt Anſwer, 2 <hi>Sam.</hi> 20.19. It appears yet more by the People of <hi>Iſraels</hi> Expoſtulating with <hi>David,</hi> why the Children of <hi>Judah</hi> ſhould Steal him, and not ask their Advice firſt, in bringing him back, 2 <hi>Sam.</hi> 19.41, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Further, We find God himſelf ſo far owning the Peoples Right to have ſatisfaction for injuries ſuffered from their King contrary to the publick Faith, that the Famine was to ceaſe on no other Terms than till the <hi>Gibeonites</hi> were Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venged upon <hi>Saul</hi> in his Poſterity, for ſeeking to Slay them, that he might pleaſe his other Subjects, 2 <hi>Sam.</hi> 21.</p>
            <p>In 1 <hi>Kings</hi> 12.7. We find the Old Men, who had Expe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rience of <hi>Solomons</hi> Reign, and knew the Conſtitution of the Kingdom, adviſing King <hi>Rehoboam,</hi> that he muſt be the <hi>Peoples Servant,</hi> if he would have them to be his: And upon his rejecting this Counſel (by the Advice of young Hectoring Tories) they rejected him.</p>
            <p>We find alſo that Kings were ſubject to Cenſures, as well as others, in the Example of <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>zziah,</hi> who becauſe of Invading the Prieſts Office, and being ſmitten with a Le<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proſie, was thruſt out of the Temple by Fourſcore Valiant Prieſts, 2 <hi>Chron.</hi> 26. Being cut off from the Houſe of the Lord, according to the Levitical Law.</p>
            <p>By this time I ſuppoſe the Reader is ſufficiently convinced that the Kings of <hi>Iſrael</hi> were the Peoples Creatures, and
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:101772:10"/>accountable to them for Male Adminiſtration: And if thoſe Kings were ſo, who were Named by God himſelf, much more they who have no other Right to any Soveraignty, but the Peoples Choice; and that Kings now adays have any other Title, for my own part, I ſhall never believe, until, as Worthy Collonel <hi>Sidney</hi> ſaid, <hi>They can deduce their Pedigree from the Eldeſt Son of</hi> Noah, <hi>and ſhew that the Succeſſion had ſtill continued in the Eldeſt of the Eldeſt Line, and ſo de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcended to them:</hi> Or as Collonel <hi>Rumbold</hi> ſaid, <hi>Till I ſee one Born with a Crown upon his Head.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Certainly there is no Reaſonable man, but muſt needs ſee the Abſurdity of that Poſition, <hi>That Kings have a Here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ditary Right, any other way, then as the People are willing, and conſent it ſhould be ſo;</hi> otherwiſe Kings might ſell their Titles to whom they pleaſe, cut off the Entail, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> and do any other thing that a Man may do with his private Eſtate, which yet they that hold that Opinion are not ſo Impudent to Aſſert.</p>
            <p>Neither does it at all reflect upon the Honour and Dig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity of Kings, nor render their Authority leſs Sacred and Inviolable, that ſome Perſons who have carried that Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour, are or may be called to an Account for Male-Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miniſtration; no more then it reflects upon the Honour of Divines, Phyſicians, or Lawyers, when ſome of their Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſions are condemned for Murder, Adultery, or Bribery, ſeeing they are not called to the Bar, and Condemned as Phyſicians, Divines, or Lawyers, but as Murderers, Adul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terers, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> And therefore ſeeing the Regal Power is limited, as we have ſeen in <hi>Deut.</hi> 17. <hi>&amp;c.</hi> and may ſee alſo in the New Teſtament, <hi>Rom.</hi> 13. where his Office is plainly ſaid to be for the <hi>encouragement of the good, and puniſhment of the bad:</hi> If Kings tranſgreſs theſe Limits, invert the end of their Commiſſion, encourage the Bad, and ſuppreſs the Good, they cannot without a plain Contradiction to the Apoſtolical Definition of a Magiſtrate, be looked upon as ſuch, in Tranſgreſſing their bounds; and without all per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>adventure, may be reſiſted in ſuch Actions, without the
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:101772:11"/>leaſt diminution of their Authority, or Affront to that Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vine and Sacred Ordinance of Magiſtracy.</p>
            <p>For the Non-probation of ſuch things as are Inſtanced in, <hi>viz.</hi> the Earl of <hi>Eſſex</hi>'s Murder, <hi>Counterfeit Prince of Wales,</hi> &amp;c: whether ever they be proved or not, it al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters not the caſe one whit, ſeeing the Repreſentatives of the Nation have adjudged him to have forfeited his Right, by ſubverting the Fundamental Laws, and deſerting the Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> Though in due time the others may be ſufficiently Evidenced to the World; but neither of their Majeſties are in the leaſt concerned to prove the Impoſture of a Counterfeit Heir; the Title being certainly in Her Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jeſty before, it lies upon the late King to make full, clear, and undoubted Proof of the others Birth, which for my own part, if it had been real, I believe would have been done in the moſt Solemn manner in World, ſeeing they knew the Nations Jealouſie aforeſaid. But being Conſcious to them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves of the Cheat, they managed it the beſt they could, to Amuſe and leave the Kingdoms in an uncertainty. How ea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſie had it been to have had Proteſtant Ladies always At<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tended the Queen, that might have been undoubted Wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſes of her Pregnancy, and the Childs Birth? And can any think, if Honeſty had been deſigned, that ſuch a thing would have been Omitted, ſeeing they knew the Suſpition to be Univerſally through the Proteſtant World? For my own part, they that can ſwallow ſuch Objections, I think, are fit to ſhake Hands with Tranſubſtantiation, and to declare themſelves Enemies to Senſe and Reaſon.</p>
            <p>But, as I ſaid before, Though there were no Truth in that charge, yet the great Council of the Nation having judged the Throne to be Vacant upon other Conſiderations, it becomes every private Perſon to Acquieſce, and much more the Clergy, if they would not have their former Miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>carriages revived, and demonſtrate to the World, that as they were Eminently ſubſervient to the deſigns of Enſlaving us (which the beſt of them, to their Honour, have ſeen, owned, and bewailed) ſo they perſiſt in their endeavours, to
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:101772:11"/>be the Unhappy Inſtruments of our Diſtraction. Though I dare ſay, That the moſt Zealous Sticklers on the late Kings ſide, are neither amongſt the Learned nor Godly of the Church, and are better verſed in <hi>Ovid de Arte Amandi,</hi> then either Politicks or Divinity; and perhaps, the great<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt effort they ever gave of their Genius, was by a Courtſhip to ſome Gentlemans Kinſwoman or Servant, to Worm them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves into a Benefice, and may well be thought none of the ſitteſt to meddle either in Affairs of Church or State: <hi>Ne Sutor ultra Crepidam.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>To Conclude, Tho' it be certain, that the generality of the Church Communion be in reference to publick Affairs, wiſer then many of their Teachers, as appears by their Eſpouſing the True Intereſt of the Nation and Religion, yet it were to be wiſhed, that the Eſtabliſhed National Church would give ſome publick Evidence of their diſlike of the preſent Rebellious practices of ſome of thoſe of her Commu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion, by a general Abhorrence or Excommunication, which certainly they have much more reaſon to do, then in the late times, to Excommunicate the whole Church and King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom of <hi>Scotland,</hi> for reſiſting the Tyrannical Impoſitions of <hi>Charles</hi> the Firſt, or yet of Excommunicating Diſſenters in the late Times, to Incapacitate them to chooſe Parliament-Men, of ſo much Courage and Honeſty, as to oppoſe Popery and Tyranny; which if God, by King <hi>William,</hi> had not delivered us from, would in probability have ſwallowed us up e'er now.</p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
